<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Celso Mireles</title>
    <description>A place for thoughts and stuff.</description>
    <link>http://celsomireles.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://celsomireles.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2016 17:06:40 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2016 17:06:40 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lessons from my first Creatathon</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend I participated in Arizona’s first Creatathon. The idea of the event is to get teams of creatives into a room for 24 hours to deliver pro-bono value to 7 Arizona nonprofits. I served as team lead for the Big Brothers Big Sisters of Central Arizona (BBBSAZ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from this experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, what did we create for BBBSAZ? I think we came out with a pretty good list of deliverables:
Animated Video
Marketing Plan
Print Collateral
&lt;a href=&quot;http://gobigbrother.org/&quot;&gt;Microsite&lt;/a&gt; to tie it all together&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My role was project lead and developer, and I learned a lot about how to manage while doing the work. It only really works when you have a team of capable and self-motivated members. And I was lucky that everyone in the team stepped up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My management style leans more towards a laissez faire style. I tend to think people don’t need so much ‘management’ as they do ‘coaching’ to get the work done. I have had mixed results with this approach however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after a conversation with my wife, I was reminded that it really depends on the make-up of the team you are working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a matrix with the following axes to consider:
- Capable
- Motivated&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;very-capable-and-highly-motivated&quot;&gt;Very Capable and Highly Motivated&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the ideal situation for a manager. This means you don’t really have to be a hard ass. You can lean on your team’s expertise to guide themselves and all you have to do is check in and keep the team motivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;very-capable-and-not-motivated&quot;&gt;Very Capable and Not Motivated&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be challenging situation. This usually calls for constant checking in and ‘holding people accountable’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underlying issue to address, however, is why the person is not motivated. If we are talking about an employee or paid contractor the reasons may be:
- Not enough pay
- Project is not challenging
- Don’t have any creative freedom in project&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are talking about a volunteer, then some reasons may be:
- Don’t resonate with the effort’s mission
- Don’t have any creative freedom in the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-capable-but-highly-motivated&quot;&gt;Not Capable but Highly Motivated&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach requires patience and an aptitude for training. Here you have to serve as manager and trainer to get your team up to speed on whatever the project goal is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens a lot when doing social justice work. You may have people willing to help, but you have to train them to do the task at hand. These are volunteers that just ‘show up’ at your door and now you have to figure out how to keep them with your organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-capable-and-not-motivated&quot;&gt;Not Capable and Not Motivated&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst situation to be in. At this point you have to ask the person, “Why are you here?” And you have to consider letting that team member go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, the experience of working with a creative team was great. It really opened my eyes to the possibilities. So far, most of my work has been done individually, and I realize that collaborative work is the way to go, but so far I have held back. Most likey due to fears, and self-doubt over my own management style. This experience served to validate my belief:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Micromanagement doesn’t need to happen when you have a team a capable and motivated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal is to create a network of capable and motivated individuals in order to take on projects that make a difference in this world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2015 06:58:35 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://celsomireles.com/lessons-from-my-first-creatathon</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://celsomireles.com/lessons-from-my-first-creatathon</guid>
        
        
        <category>management</category>
        
        <category>probono</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on the Hamburger Menu</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I must admit, I would internally roll my eyes when friends bash on the now famous &lt;em&gt;Hamburger Menu&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d just nod and smile, and think&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;but it’s such a genius design. It solves the problem of precious real estate on mobile screens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess those friends never really explained &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the Hamburger Menu was so annoying. But I recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://deep.design/the-hamburger-menu/&quot;&gt;read a piece&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jamesarcher.me/&quot;&gt;James Archer&lt;/a&gt; that opened my eyes as to the utilitarian reason for not using this design pattern as the primary navigation for a site or app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is that by using the Hamburger Menu, you are essentially hiding content from the user, and no matter how much you want them to, users will &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; click on it to find what they are looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a good read, for sure, and now I’m thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How can implement this in my own work… right now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I have a client whose website I’m currently redesigning, and she may benefit from this. I will brainstorm on how to implement this new nugget of wisdom immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of immediately, I am adding it to my to-do list right now to take out the hamburger icon out from this website. We’ll see how that goes, seeing as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The cobbler’s children are always the worst-shod.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is actually a good topic for another post…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2015 15:08:35 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://celsomireles.com/thoughts-on-the-hamburger-menu</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://celsomireles.com/thoughts-on-the-hamburger-menu</guid>
        
        
        <category>design</category>
        
        <category>mobile</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Change of Scenery</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven’t really had an online space to share some writing lately. I used to have a WordPress site, but that was too complicated to handle for just a simple blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I needed something simple, easy to use, and that would make me feel like a total tech nerd. Needless to say, I welcomed Jekyll with open arms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 15:08:35 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://celsomireles.com/change-of-scenery</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://celsomireles.com/change-of-scenery</guid>
        
        
        <category>career,</category>
        
        <category>website</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
